<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
     xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
     xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
     xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
     xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
     >
  <channel>
    <title>The Kitchin Research Group</title>
    <link>http://jkitchin.github.io/blog</link>
    <description>Chemical Engineering at Carnegie Mellon University</description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2014 20:08:37 GMT</pubDate>
    <generator>Blogofile</generator>
    <sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
    <sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
    <item>
      <title>New publication in RSC Advances</title>
      <link>http://jkitchin.github.io/blog/2014/02/20/New-publication-in-RSC-Advances</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2014 15:08:12 EST</pubDate>
      <category><![CDATA[news]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[publication]]></category>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">Q5ifrdwWBRYKi_3xDmv5lK37CnA=</guid>
      <description>New publication in RSC Advances</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[


<div id="table-of-contents">
<h2>Table of Contents</h2>
<div id="text-table-of-contents">
<ul>
<li><a href="#sec-1">1. Bibtex entry</a></li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>

<p>
A collaborative paper with our colleagues at NETL and U. Pitt. was just accepted in RSC Advances <pre>cite:thompson-2014-co2-react</pre> !
</p>

<div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="sec-1"><span class="section-number-2">1</span> Bibtex entry</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1">
<p>
#+BEGIN<sub>SRC</sub>: :tangle /tmp/extract-bib269688VI.bib
@Article{thompson-2014-co2-react,
  author =         {Thompson, Robert L. and Albenze, Erik and Shi, Wei
                  and Hopkinson, David and Damodaran, Krishnan and
                  Lee, Anita and Kitchin, John and Luebke, David
                  Richard and Nulwala, Hunaid},
  title =         {\ce{CO_2} Reactive Ionic Liquids: Effects of
                  functional groups on the anion and its influence on
                  the physical properties},
  journal =         {RSC Adv.},
  year =         2014,
  pages =         "-",
  publisher =         {The Royal Society of Chemistry},
  doi =                 {10.1039/C3RA47097K},
  url =                 {<a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1039/C3RA47097K">http://dx.doi.org/10.1039/C3RA47097K</a> },
  abstract =         "Next generation of gas separation materials are
                  needed to alleviate issues faced in energy and
                  environmental area. Ionic liquids (ILs) are
                  promising class of material for CO2 separations. In
                  this work{,} CO2 reactive triazolides ILs were
                  synthesized and characterized with the aim of
                  developing deeper understanding on how structural
                  changes affect the overall properties for CO2
                  separation. Important insights were gained
                  illustrating the effects of substituents on the
                  anion. It was found that substituents play a crucial
                  role in dictating the overall physical properties of
                  reactive ionic liquids. Depending upon the
                  electronic and steric nature of the substituent{,}
                  CO2 capacities between 0.07-0.4 mol CO2/mol IL were
                  observed. Detailed spectroscopic{,} CO2
                  absorption{,} rheological{,} and simulation studies
                  were carried out to understand the nature and
                  influence of these substituents. The effect of water
                  content was also evaluated{,} and it was found that
                  water had an unexpected impact on the properties of
                  these materials{,} resulting in an increased
                  viscosity{,} but little change in the CO2
                  reactivity."
}
#+END<sub>SRC</sub></p>
</div>
</div>
<p>Copyright (C) 2014 by John Kitchin. See the <a href="/copying.html">License</a> for information about copying.<p><p><a href="/org/2014/02/20/New-publication-in-RSC-Advances.org">org-mode source</a><p><p>Org-mode version = 8.2.5h</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New publication in Applied Materials and Interfaces</title>
      <link>http://jkitchin.github.io/blog/2014/02/06/New-publication-in-Applied-Materials-and-Interfaces</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2014 16:04:06 EST</pubDate>
      <category><![CDATA[news]]></category>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">dq98SZyXWUQwhQ3N8aPH63guxMo=</guid>
      <description>New publication in Applied Materials and Interfaces</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[


<p>
<b>Identifying Potential BO2 Oxide Polymorphs for Epitaxial Growth Candidates</b>,
by Prateek Mehta, Paul A. Salvador, and John R. Kitchin
<a href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/full/10.1021/am4059149">http://pubs.acs.org/doi/full/10.1021/am4059149</a> 
</p>

<p>
Transition metal dioxides (BO2) exhibit a number of polymorphic structures with distinct properties, but the isolation of different polymorphs for a given composition is carried out using trial and error experimentation. We present computational studies of the relative stabilities and equations of state for six polymorphs (anatase, brookite, rutile, columbite, pyrite, and fluorite) of five different BO2 dioxides (B = Ti, V, Ru, Ir, and Sn). These properties were computed in a consistent fashion using several exchange correlation functionals within the density functional theory formalism, and the effects of the different functionals are discussed relative to their impact on predictive synthesis. We compare the computational results to prior observations of high-pressure synthesis and epitaxial film growth and then use this discussion to predict new accessible polymorphs in the context of epitaxial stabilization using isostructural substrates. For example, the relative stabilities of the columbite polymorph for VO2 and RuO2 are similar to those of TiO2 and SnO2, the latter two of which have been previously stabilized as epitaxial films.
</p>

<p>
As with other recent papers, the supporting information file contains embedded data files that enable the reproduction of the data and figures in the paper.
</p>
<p>Copyright (C) 2014 by John Kitchin. See the <a href="/copying.html">License</a> for information about copying.<p><p><a href="/org/2014/02/06/New-publication-in-Applied-Materials-and-Interfaces.org">org-mode source</a><p><p>Org-mode version = 8.2.5h</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New MS students join the Kitchin Research Group</title>
      <link>http://jkitchin.github.io/blog/2013/12/13/New-MS-students-join-the-Kitchin-Research-Group</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2013 10:50:16 EST</pubDate>
      <category><![CDATA[news]]></category>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">Y6j7mC0g4SW--pI6dJjo5rdZGsw=</guid>
      <description>New MS students join the Kitchin Research Group</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[


<p>
Three new M.S. students have joined the Kitchin Research Group! We are pleased to welcome Wenqin You, Meiheng Lu, and Nitish Govindarajan!
</p>

<p>
Wenqin will work on modeling CO2 capture processes, Meiheng will work on a data sharing project, and Nitish will use density functional theory to model oxide materials relevant to SOFCs and CO2 conversion.
</p>
<p>Copyright (C) 2014 by John Kitchin. See the <a href="/copying.html">License</a> for information about copying.<p><p><a href="/org/2013/12/13/New-MS-students-join-the-Kitchin-Research-Group.org">org-mode source</a><p><p>Org-mode version = 8.2.5c</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New PhD students join the Kitchin Research Group</title>
      <link>http://jkitchin.github.io/blog/2013/11/15/New-PhD-students-join-the-Kitchin-Research-Group</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2013 10:50:16 EST</pubDate>
      <category><![CDATA[news]]></category>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">QbqWuDw-SwgwLFToEW9RBFEyYbY=</guid>
      <description>New PhD students join the Kitchin Research Group</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[


<p>
Three new PhD students have joined the Kitchin Research Group! We are pleased to welcome Mehak Chawla, Qingqi (Victor) Fan, and John Michael (co-advised by Professor Paul Sides) to the group.
</p>

<p>
Mehak joins us from The Ohio State University. She will be using density functional theory to model metal alloy and oxide surface reactivity.
</p>

<p>
John completed his B.S. in Chemical Engineering at Miami University (OH). He will be using the imaging ammeter to screen electrocatalysts. He will be co-advised by Dr. Sides.
</p>

<p>
Victor joins us from the University of Tulsa. He will be studying oxygen evolution electrocatalysis on transition metal oxides.
</p>
<p>Copyright (C) 2013 by John Kitchin. See the <a href="/copying.html">License</a> for information about copying.<p><p><a href="/org/2013/11/15/New-PhD-students-join-the-Kitchin-Research-Group.org">org-mode source</a><p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New publication in Topics in Catalysis</title>
      <link>http://jkitchin.github.io/blog/2013/11/11/New-publication-in-Topics-in-Catalysis</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2013 20:20:28 EST</pubDate>
      <category><![CDATA[news]]></category>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">OOrd6rRlpTyEHIaivGLZZ9sCMfQ=</guid>
      <description>New publication in Topics in Catalysis</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[


<p>
:END:
</p>


<p>
Simulating Temperature Programmed Desorption of Oxygen on Pt(111) Using DFT Derived Coverage Dependent Desorption Barriers

    Spencer D. Miller,
    Vladimir V. Pushkarev,
    Andrew J. Gellman,
    John R. Kitchin 

<a href="http://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11244-013-0166-3">http://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11244-013-0166-3</a> 

Abstract

The dissociative adsorption energy of oxygen on Pt(111) is known to be coverage dependent. Simple Redhead analysis of temperature programmed desorption (TPD) experiments that assumes a coverage independent desorption barrier can lead to errors in estimated properties such as desorption barriers and adsorption energies. A simple correction is to assume a linear coverage dependence of the desorption barrier, but there is usually no formal justification given for that functional form. More advanced TPD analysis methods that are suitable for determining coverage dependent adsorption parameters are limited by their need for large amounts of high quality, low noise data. We present a method to estimate the functional form of the coverage dependent desorption barrier from density functional theory calculations for use in analysis of TPD spectra. Density functional theory was employed to calculate the coverage dependence of the adsorption energy. Simulated TPD spectra were then produced by empirically scaling the DFT based adsorption energies utilizing the Bronstead-Evans-Polyani relationship between adsorption energies and desorption barriers. The resulting simulated spectra show better agreement with the experimental spectra than spectra predicted using barriers that are either coverage-independent or simply linearly dependent on coverage. The empirically derived scaling of the desorption barriers for Pt(111) is shown to be useful in predicting the low coverage desorption barriers for oxygen desorption from other metal surfaces, which showed reasonable agreement with the reported experimental values for those other metals.

The <a href="http://link.springer.com/content/esm/art:10.1007/s11244-013-0166-3/file/MediaObjects/11244_2013_166_MOESM1_ESM.pdf">supporting information</a> file is especially interesting because it has nearly all of the data files used in the paper embedded in it!
</p>
<p>Copyright (C) 2013 by John Kitchin. See the <a href="/copying.html">License</a> for information about copying.<p><p><a href="/org/2013/11/11/New-publication-in-Topics-in-Catalysis.org">org-mode source</a><p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New publication in Catalysis Communications</title>
      <link>http://jkitchin.github.io/blog/2013/11/11/New-publication-in-Catalysis-Communications</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2013 20:18:15 EST</pubDate>
      <category><![CDATA[news]]></category>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">84OjMTcoTk-8WIeTrpSPvp3_XXA=</guid>
      <description>New publication in Catalysis Communications</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[



<p>
Relating the Electronic Structure and Reactivity of the 3d Transition Metal Monoxide Surfaces
</p>

<p>
Zhongnan Xu, and  John R. Kitchin
</p>

<p>
We performed a series of density functional theory calculations of dissociative oxygen adsorption on fcc metals and their corresponding rocksalt monoxides to elucidate the relationship between the oxide electronic structure and its corresponding reactivity. We decomposed the dissociative adsorption energy of oxygen on an oxide surface into a sum of the adsorption energy on the metal and a change in adsorption energy caused by both expanding and oxidizing the lattice. We were able to identify the key features of the electronic structure that explains the trends in adsorption energies on 3d transition metal monoxide surfaces.
</p>

<p>
<a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.catcom.2013.10.028">http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.catcom.2013.10.028</a> 
</p>
<p>Copyright (C) 2013 by John Kitchin. See the <a href="/copying.html">License</a> for information about copying.<p><p><a href="/org/2013/11/11/New-publication-in-Catalysis-Communications.org">org-mode source</a><p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Professor Kitchin attended the World Congress of Chemical Engineering in Seoul, Korea</title>
      <link>http://jkitchin.github.io/blog/2013/08/27/Professor-Kitchin-attended-the-World-Congress-of-Chemical-Engineering-in-Seoul-Korea</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2013 20:59:27 EDT</pubDate>
      <category><![CDATA[news]]></category>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">vsU3jO62CKlyI-OnGEFTIIKWTmM=</guid>
      <description>Professor Kitchin attended the World Congress of Chemical Engineering in Seoul, Korea</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[


<p>
The meeting took place August 18-23. See  <a href="http://www.wcce9.org/">http://www.wcce9.org/</a> for more information.
</p>
<p>Copyright (C) 2013 by John Kitchin. See the <a href="/copying.html">License</a> for information about copying.<p><p><a href="/org/2013/08/27/Professor-Kitchin-attended-the-World-Congress-of-Chemical-Engineering-in-Seoul,-Korea.org">org-mode source</a><p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New paper on SO2 tolerance of CO2 sorbent accepted in I&ECR</title>
      <link>http://jkitchin.github.io/blog/2013/07/09/New-paper-on-SO2-tolerance-of-CO2-sorbent-accepted-in-I-ECR</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2013 07:16:49 EDT</pubDate>
      <category><![CDATA[news]]></category>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">WB0w5x8-HIQ6ebqF1ZX1ePBGLm0=</guid>
      <description>New paper on SO2 tolerance of CO2 sorbent accepted in I&ECR</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[


<p>
Our paper "Effects of O2 and SO2 on the capture capacity of a primary-amine based polymeric CO2 sorbent" by Alexander Hallenbeck and John R. Kitchin was accepted today in Industrial &amp; Engineering Chemistry Research. In this paper we showed that the ion exchange resin OC1065 is  susceptible to poisoning by SO2, but that it can be partially chemically regenerated. It can also be damaged by long term exposure to air at elevated temperatures.
</p>
<p>Copyright (C) 2013 by John Kitchin. See the <a href="/copying.html">License</a> for information about copying.<p><p><a href="/org/2013/07/09/New-paper-on-SO2-tolerance-of-CO2-sorbent-accepted-in-I&ECR.org">org-mode source</a><p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New paper accepted on CO_2 capture simulation</title>
      <link>http://jkitchin.github.io/blog/2013/06/25/New-paper-accepted-on-CO-2-capture-simulation</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2013 04:54:00 EDT</pubDate>
      <category><![CDATA[news]]></category>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">-UT_jWysyzk-2RDSOFZKwCXZgJw=</guid>
      <description>New paper accepted on CO_2 capture simulation</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[


<p>
Our manuscript titled "Comparisons of Amine Solvents for Post-combustion CO\(_2\) Capture: A Multi-objective Analysis Approach" by Anita Lee, John Eslick, David Miller, and John Kitchin was just accepted in International Journal of Greenhouse Gas Control. In this paper we used a genetic algorithm to find pareto-optimal operating conditions of amine solvent CO2 capture systems that minimize capital cost and parasitic power cost. We compared MEA, DEA and AMP, and found that there are operating conditions where both solvents could be better than MEA.
</p>

<p>
Update: The article is online here:  <a href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1750583613002703">http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1750583613002703</a> 
</p>
<p>Copyright (C) 2013 by John Kitchin. See the <a href="/copying.html">License</a> for information about copying.<p><p><a href="/org/2013/06/25/New-paper-accepted-on-CO_2-capture-simulation.org">org-mode source</a><p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Zhongnan Xu receives an ICMR International Research Fellowship</title>
      <link>http://jkitchin.github.io/blog/2013/05/24/Zhongnan-Xu-receives-an-ICMR-International-Research-Fellowship</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 May 2013 09:41:40 EDT</pubDate>
      <category><![CDATA[news]]></category>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">jjK9mIzqDfO_yNYaX1HQOEBty2A=</guid>
      <description>Zhongnan Xu receives an ICMR International Research Fellowship</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[


<p>
Zhongnan will be visiting the Denmark Technical University to collaborate with Jan Rossmeisl in the next year! This fellowship is supported by the IMI Program of the National Science Foundation under Award No. DMR 08-43934 through UC Santa Barbara. Congratulations Zhongnan!</p>
<p>Copyright (C) 2013 by John Kitchin. See the <a href="/copying.html">License</a> for information about copying.<p><p><a href="/org/2013/05/24/Zhongnan-Xu-receives-an-ICMR-International-Research-Fellowship.org">org-mode source</a><p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
