<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed
  xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:thr="http://purl.org/syndication/thread/1.0"
  xml:lang="en"
   >
  <title type="text">The Kitchin Research Group</title>
  <subtitle type="text">Chemical Engineering at Carnegie Mellon University</subtitle>

  <updated>2015-11-21T00:32:23Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://blogofile.com/">Blogofile</generator>

  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://jkitchin.github.io/blog" />
  <id>http://jkitchin.github.io/blog/feed/atom/</id>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://jkitchin.github.io/blog/feed/atom/" />
  <entry>
    <author>
      <name></name>
      <uri>http://jkitchin.github.io/blog</uri>
    </author>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Update on org-ref - it is now all emacs-lisp]]></title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://jkitchin.github.io/blog/2015/03/16/Update-on-org-ref-it-is-now-all-emacs-lisp" />
    <id>http://jkitchin.github.io/blog/2015/03/16/Update-on-org-ref-it-is-now-all-emacs-lisp</id>
    <updated>2015-03-16T08:51:50Z</updated>
    <published>2015-03-16T08:51:50Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://jkitchin.github.io/blog" term="orgmode" />
    <category scheme="http://jkitchin.github.io/blog" term="orgref" />
    <category scheme="http://jkitchin.github.io/blog" term="emacs" />
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Update on org-ref - it is now all emacs-lisp]]></summary>
    <content type="html" xml:base="http://jkitchin.github.io/blog/2015/03/16/Update-on-org-ref-it-is-now-all-emacs-lisp"><![CDATA[



<p>
The <a href="https://github.com/jkitchin/org-ref">org-ref</a> code is finally all in emacs-lisp! This should make it much easier to install, and is another step closer to getting org-ref into MELPA. Previously, I had written the most significant code in org-mode source blocks that were intended to be tangled out. I found this was not really portable, because what gets tangled depends on your org-mode setup. I had to specifically set example blocks to not tangle, or org-ref would not work for other people, and if I forgot to set a block to tangle, it also would not work for others. That should not happen again now, since there is no more tangling.
</p>


<p>
There are some relatively new features in org-ref:
</p>
<ol class="org-ol">
<li>New colored org-ref links to differentiate them from other
org-links. Citations are greenish, refs and labels are maroonish.
</li>
<li>Context messages about links. With your cursor on a cite, ref or label link
you will get a context message, e.g. a formatted citation, some context about
the label a ref refers to, or a count of the labels in the mini-buffer.
</li>
<li>There is now an org-ref menu in the Org menu.
</li>
<li>There is a new org-ref-help function that opens an org-file of org-ref
documentation.
</li>
<li>Pretty thorough integration of helm throughout org-ref, and some integration
of hydra.
</li>
<li>A few utility libraries: doi-utils, isbn, wos, pubmed, arxiv, jmax-bibtex, sci-id,
x2bib. Not all these are new, but if you didn't know about them, check them out.
</li>
<li>Cask integration. This mostly provides access to testing and dependencies
right now. org-ref is also now tested continuously at
<a href="https://travis-ci.org/jkitchin/org-ref">https://travis-ci.org/jkitchin/org-ref</a> .
</li>
</ol>

<p>
org-ref is basically feature complete I think (which is to say that once again, I do not have any big ideas for new features ;). There are some places where it could be refactored a little, e.g. there are some bibtex only functions in org-ref.el that really should go into jmax-bibtex.el (which also could be renamed). This is a very low priority though, because things are working fine as far as I can tell.
</p>

<p>
What does it need before going into MELPA? Probably some tests would be a good idea. On Travis, all that is really tested is that it loads with no errors. I would like to see some stability on my end, e.g. at least a week where no commits get made, and no errors are reported. And finally, I would like to make sure I have some time to handle issues that come up when a broader audience is trying it out.
</p>

<p>
My target date to get this in MELPA is June 1, 2015. Try out the new org-ref, and let me know how it goes!</p>
<p>Copyright (C) 2015 by John Kitchin. See the <a href="/copying.html">License</a> for information about copying.<p><p><a href="/org/2015/03/16/Update-on-org-ref---it-is-now-all-emacs-lisp.org">org-mode source</a><p><p>Org-mode version = 8.2.10</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
</feed>
